<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<info>
  <title>Python-ASN1 reference manual</title>
  <author><firstname>Geert</firstname> <surname>Jansen</surname> </author>
  <copyright><year>2007-2008</year> <holder>Geert Jansen</holder> </copyright>
</info>
<preface>
  <title>Foreword</title>
</preface>

<chapter>
  <title>Introduction to ASN.1</title>

  <para>
  ASN.1 is short for <emphasis>Abstract Syntax Notation One</emphasis>
  <citation>ASN1</citation>. It is a joint ISO/IEC and ITU-T standard  for
  describing the syntax and encoding of data structures in a platform
  independent way. The syntax of data structures in ASN.1 is described by a
  syntax definiton language. This language is used to compose ever more
  complex data types from a few simple ones such as integer and string. Often
  you will see this language in other standards that define an application on
  top of ASN.1 (for example LDAP). It is outside the scope of this
  introduction to go any deeper into the ASN.1 syntax definition language.
  </para>

  <para>
  The encoding of data structures in ASN.1 is defined by so-called
  <firstterm>encoding rules</firstterm>. Not just one but many encoding rules
  exist, and occasionally new ones are added. Each of the encoding rules is
  powerful enough to encode any data type specified by the ASN.1 language.
  Because of the multiple encoding rules, it also means that is it not enough
  to know that a piece of data is ASN.1 to decode it: you also need to know
  the encoding rules with which it was encoded.
  </para>

  <para>
  ASN.1 was first conceived in 1984. Some people say it is old, other say it
  is mature. Fact is that many Internet protocols are built on top of ASN.1.
  Some of the most important of these protocols are:

  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem> LDAP (Lightweight Directory Access Protocol) </listitem>
  <listitem> Kerberos (network authentication protocol) </listitem>
  <listitem> SNMP (Simple Network Management Protocol) </listitem>
  <listitem> X.509 (public key infrastructure, known from e.g. SSL
  certificates) </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  </para>

  <para>
  ASN.1 is not the only standard for defining the syntax and encoding of data
  structures. Other standards are Sun's XDR (External Data Representation,
  <citation>XDR</citation>), and EBNF (Extended Backus-Naur Form,
  <citation>EBNF</citation>). XDR is used primarily for
  ONC-RPC applications such as NFS (the Network File System). EBNF is perhaps
  the most used standard of them all: HTTP and XML (and thereby all its
  applications) are specified in EBNF.
  </para>

  <para>
  But now back to ASN.1... ASN.1 data types are either primitive data types
  such as integers and strings, or more complex ones built on them. Whatever
  the details of the data type, each of them has the following properties.

  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
  <emphasis>Its number.</emphasis> The number is a numerical identifier that
  identifies the data type uniquely amongst others in its class. For example,
  ASN.1 defines that the type <quote>integer</quote> has the number
  <quote>2</quote>.
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
  <emphasis>Its class.</emphasis> Four classes exist:
  <emphasis>universal</emphasis>, <emphasis>application</emphasis>,
  <emphasis>context</emphasis>, <emphasis>private</emphasis>. Each class
  defines the scope of the data type, i.e. how broad is the type available.
  Universal types are always available while the other ones are more
  restricted.  All standard primitive types that are defined by ASN.1 are
  defined in the universal class.
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
  <emphasis>Its encoding type (or just <quote>type</quote>).</emphasis> Two
  types exist: <emphasis>primitive</emphasis> and
  <emphasis>constructed</emphasis>. Primitively types contain just one data
  value such as a number or a string, while constructed types contain a
  collection of other primitive and/or constructed types.
  </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  The three properties together (number, class, type) are also called the
  <firstterm>tag</firstterm> of a data type.
  </para>

  <para>
  As mentioned above, the encoding of data structures is defined by ASN.1
  encoding rules. The most well-known encodings rules are:
  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>BER (Basic Encoding Rules) </listitem>
  <listitem>DER (Distinguished Encoding Rules</listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  We now go into a little more detail on BER and DER because understanding of
  it helps you to understand the Python-AD API.
  </para>

  <para>
  The BER and DER encodings are very similar: BER is a looser format and
  sometimes allows a single value to be encoded in different ways. The DER is
  a subset of BER and defines in case multiple encodings are possible which
  one needs to be used. This means that a BER parser can read DER (because
  that is just a special form of BER), and a DER generator automatically
  generates valid BER (because all DER is also BER.)
  </para>

  <para>
  Python-ASN1 supports the DER and BER, and none of the other encoding rules.
  The vast majority of applications use these encoding rules, so at the moment
  no support for additional encoding rules is planned. When generating ASN.1,
  Python-AD will output DER, while for parsing it supports BER. This
  arrangement complies with the practise of being forgiving on input, and
  strict on output.
  </para>

  <para>
  The DER and BER encodings work according the the <firstterm>TLV</firstterm>
  (Tag, Length, Value) principle. A stream of encoded ASN.1 data consists of a
  sequence of zero or more (tags, lenght, value) tuples, one after the other.
  These tuples are also called <firstterm>records</firstterm> in this manual,
  although this is not a term that is defined in the ASN.1 standard. For each
  data type, DER and BER define how to encode the tag (which we remember is a
  combination of its number, class and type), the length (in octets) of the
  data value, and the data value itself.
  </para>

  <bibliolist>
  <biblioentry>
    <abbrev>ASN1</abbrev>
    <link xlink:href="http://www.itu.int/ITU-T/studygroups/com17/languages/">
    ITU-T Study Group 17 - Languages for Telecommunication Systems</link>
  </biblioentry>
  <biblioentry>
    <abbrev>XDR</abbrev>
    <link xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4506">XDR: External
    Data Representation Standard</link>
  </biblioentry>
  <biblioentry>
    <abbrev>EBNF</abbrev>
    <link xlink:href="http://standards.iso.org/ittf/PubliclyAvailableStandards/s026153_ISO_IEC_14977_1996(E).zip">
  ISO/IEC 14977: Information technology -- Syntactic metalanguage -- Extended
  BNF</link>
  </biblioentry>
  </bibliolist>
</chapter>

<chapter>
  <title>API reference</title>
  
  <section>
  <title>Overview</title>

  <para>
  This section provides a general, high-level overview of the API. The API is
  explained in full detail in the sections that follow.
  </para>

  <para>
  The Python-ASN1 API is exposed by a single Python module named
  <literal>asn1</literal>. The main interface is provided by the following
  classes:

  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem><classname>Encoder</classname>: Used to encode ASN.1. </listitem>
  <listitem><classname>Decoder</classname>: Used to decode ASN.1. </listitem>
  <listitem><classname>Error</classname>: Exception used to signal errors.
  </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  </para>

  <para>
  The interface names on purpose do not repeat <quote>ASN1</quote> in their
  names: the encoder is called <literal>Encoder</literal> and not
  <literal>ASN1Encoder</literal>. The fact that they live in the
  <literal>asn1</literal> module makes their names already unique. Because of
  this naming convention, there are two recommended ways to import the module.
  The first way is to import the module only, and use that to access the
  interface classes, as is illustrated below:

  <programlisting>
  import asn1

  # Use asn1.Encoder, etc.
  </programlisting>
  </para>

  <para>
  The second way to use the API is to import the interface classes direclty
  but add <quote>ASN1</quote> to their names:

  <programlisting>
  from asn1 import Encoder as ASN1Encoder

  # use ASN1Encoder
  </programlisting>

  This way the risk of namespace conflicts is minimized.
  </para>

  </section>

  <section>
  <title>Type Mapping</title>

  <para>
  The Python-ASN1 encoder and decoder make a difference between primitive and
  constructed data types. Primitive data types can be encoded and decoded
  directly with <methodname>read()</methodname> and
  <methodname>write()</methodname> methods.  For these types, ASN.1 types are
  mapped directly to Python types and vice versa, as per the table below:

  <informaltable align="center">
  <tgroup cols="3">
  <thead>
    <row> <entry> ASN.1 Type </entry> <entry> Python type </entry>
          <entry> Default </entry> </row>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <row> <entry> Boolean </entry> <entry> bool or int <footnote><para>
    Depending on whether the Python version supports the
    <literal>bool</literal> type </para> </footnote> </entry>
    <entry>yes/no<footnote><para>If <literal>bool</literal> is available then that
    is the default type for Boolean, otherwise no default type
    exists</para></footnote>. </entry> </row>
    <row> <entry> Integer </entry> <entry> int </entry> <entry>yes</entry>
    </row>
    <row> <entry> OctetString </entry> <entry> str </entry> <entry>yes</entry>
    </row>
    <row> <entry> Null </entry> <entry> None </entry> <entry>yes</entry>
    </row>
    <row> <entry> ObjectIdentifier </entry> <entry> str </entry> <entry>no
    </entry> </row>
    <row> <entry> Enumerated </entry> <entry> int </entry> <entry>no </entry>
    </row>
  </tbody>
  </tgroup>
  </informaltable>

  The column <quote>default</quote> is relevant for encoding only.  Because
  ASN.1 has more data types than Python, the situation arises that one Python
  type corresponds to multiple ASN.1 types. In this sitution the to be encoded
  ASN.1 type cannot be determined from the Python type. The solution
  implemented in Python-ASN1 is that the most frequently used type will be the
  implicit default, and if another type is desired than that must be specified
  explicitly through the API.
  </para>

  <para>
  For constructed types, no type mapping is done at all, even for types where
  such a mapping would be possible such as the ASN.1 type <quote>sequence
  of</quote> which could be mapped to a Python list. For such types a stack
  based approach is used instead. In this approach, the user needs to
  explicitly enter/leave the constructed type using the
  <methodname>enter()</methodname> and <methodname>leave()</methodname>
  methods of the encoder and the decoder.
  </para>

  </section>

  <section>
  <title>Encoding ASN.1</title>

  <para>
  Encoding of ASN.1 data is done with the <classname>Encoder</classname> class
  that is defined in the Python package <literal>asn1</literal>.
  </para>

  <para>
  The constructor of <classname>Encoder</classname> takes no arguments.
  </para>

  <para>
  The <classname>Encoder</classname> class has the following methods:
  </para>

  <para>
  <synopsis>start()</synopsis>
  The <methodname>start()</methodname> method instructs the encoder to start
  encoding a new ASN.1 output. This method may be called at any time to
  reset the encoder, and resets the current output (if any).
  </para>

  <para>
  <synopsis>write(value, nr=None, typ=None, cls=None)</synopsis>
  The <methodname>write()</methodname> method encodes one ASN.1 record and
  writes it to the output buffer. Normally, <parameter>value</parameter> will
  be the only parameter to this method. In this case Python-AD will autodetect
  the correct ASN.1 type from the type of <parameter>value</parameter>, and
  will output the encoded value based on this type. If the desired ASN.1 type
  cannot be autodetected or is autodetected wrongly, the
  <parameter>nr</parameter> parameter can be provided to specify the ASN.1
  type to be used. The <parameter>typ</parameter> parameter can be used to
  write constructed types to the output by setting it to indicate the
  constructed encoding type (see <xref linkend="constants"/>). In this case,
  <parameter>value</parameter> must already be valid ASN.1 encoded data as a
  plain Python string. This is not normally how constructed types should be
  encoded though, see <methodname>enter()</methodname> and
  <methodname>leave()</methodname> for the recommended way of doing this. The
  <parameter>cls</parameter> argument can be used to override the class of the
  value. The default class is the universal class.
  </para>

  <para>
  <synopsis>enter(nr, cls=None)</synopsis>
  The <methodname>enter()</methodname> method starts the construction of a
  constructed type. The <parameter>nr</parameter> specifies the number of the
  type. The optional parameter <parameter>cls</parameter> specifies the class
  of the constructed type. The default class to use is the universal class.
  </para>

  <para>
  <synopsis>leave()</synopsis>
  The <methodname>leave()</methodname> method completes the construction of a
  constructed type and writes the encoded representation to the output buffer.
  </para>

  <para>
  <synopsis>output()</synopsis>
  The <methodname>output()</methodname> returns the encoded ASN.1 data as
  a plain Python string. This method can be called multiple times, also during
  encoding. In the latter case the data that has been encoded so far is
  returned. It is an error to call this method if the encoder is still
  constructing a constructed type, i.e. if <methodname>enter()</methodname>
  has been called more times that <methodname>leave()</methodname>.
  </para>

  </section>

  <section>
  <title>Decoding ASN.1</title>

  <para>
  Decoding of ASN.1 data is done with the <classname>Decoder</classname> class
  that is defined in the Python package <literal>asn1</literal>.
  </para>

  <para>
  The constructor of <classname>Decoder</classname> takes no arguments.
  </para>

  <para>
  The <classname>Decoder</classname> class has the following methods:
  </para>

  <para>
  <synopsis>start(data)</synopsis>
  The <methodname>start()</methodname> method instructs the decoder to start
  decoding the ASN.1 input <parameter>data</parameter>, which must be a passed
  in as a plain Python string. This method may be called at any time to start
  a new decoding job. If this method is called while currently decoding
  another input, that decoding context is discarded.<note>It is not
  necessary to specify the encoding because the decoder assumes the input is
  in BER/DER format.</note>
  </para>

  <para>
  <synopsis>read()</synopsis>
  The <methodname>read()</methodname> method decodes one ASN.1 record from the
  input and returns it as a <literal>(tag, value)</literal> tuple. The tag is
  a 3-tuple <literal>(nr, type, class)</literal>, while the value is a Python
  object representing the ASN.1 value. The offset in the input is increased so
  that the next <methodname>read()</methodname> call will return the next
  record. In case no more data is available from the input,
  <literal>None</literal> is returned to signal end-of-file.
  </para>

  <para>
  <synopsis>peek()</synopsis>
  The <methodname>peek()</methodname> returns the tag of the current ASN.1
  record (i.e. the record that a subsequent <methodname>read()</methodname>
  call would return) without updating the decoding offset. In case no more
  data is available from the input, None is returned to signal end-of-file.
  This method is useful if you don't know whether the next tag will be a
  primitive or a constructed tag. Depending on the return value of
  <methodname>peek()</methodname>, you would decide to either issue a
  <methodname>read()</methodname> in case of a primitive type, or an
  <methodname>enter()</methodname> in case of a constructed type.  <note>
  Because this method does not advance the current offset in the input,
  calling it multiple times in a row will return the same value for all
  calls.</note>
  </para>

  <para>
  <synopsis>eof()</synopsis>
  This method returns true if all input has been decoded, and false otherwise.
  </para>

  <para>
  <synopsis>enter()</synopsis>
  The <methodname>enter()</methodname> method enters the constructed type that
  is at the current decoding offset. It is an error to call
  <methodname>enter()</methodname> if the to be decoded ASN.1 record is not of
  a constructed type.
  </para>

  <para>
  <synopsis>leave()</synopsis>
  The <methodname>leave()</methodname> method leaves the last constructed type
  that was <methodname>enter()</methodname>-ed. It is an error to call this
  method if currently not decoding a constructed type.
  </para>

  </section>

  <section>
  <title>Error Handling</title>

  <para>
  Errors in Python-ASN1 are reported as exceptions. One exception is defined
  in the <literal>asn1</literal> module: <classname>Error</classname>.  All
  errors in Python-ASN1 are reported through this exception. This includes
  encoding errors, decoding errors and usage errors.
  </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="constants">
  <title>Constants</title>

  <para>
  A few constants are defined in the <literal>asn1</literal> module. The
  constants immediately below correspond to ASN.1 numbers. They can be used as
  the <parameter>nr</parameter> parameter of the
  <methodname>Encoder.write()</methodname> method, and are returned as the
  first part of a <literal>(nr, typ, cls)</literal> tuple as returned by
  <methodname>Decoder.peek()</methodname> and
  <methodname>Decoder.read()</methodname>.

  <programlisting>
  Boolean = 0x01
  Integer = 0x02
  OctetString = 0x04
  Null = 0x05
  ObjectIdentifier = 0x06
  Enumerated = 0x0a
  Sequence = 0x10
  Set = 0x11
  </programlisting>
  </para>

  <para>
  The following constants define the two available encoding types (primitive
  and constructed) for ASN.1 data types. As above they can be used with the
  <methodname>Encoder.write()</methodname> and are returned by
  <methodname>Decoder.peek()</methodname> and
  <methodname>Decoder.read()</methodname>.

  <programlisting>
  TypeConstructed = 0x20
  TypePrimitive = 0x00
  </programlisting>
  </para>

  <para>
  Finally the constants below define the different ASN.1 classes.  As above
  they can be used with the <methodname>Encoder.write()</methodname> and are
  returned by <methodname>Decoder.peek()</methodname> and
  <methodname>Decoder.read()</methodname>.

  <programlisting>
  ClassUniversal = 0x00
  ClassApplication = 0x40
  ClassContext = 0x80
  ClassPrivate = 0xc0
  </programlisting>
  </para>

  </section>

</chapter>

<appendix>
  <title>Credits</title>

  <para>
  The following projects have provided inspiration for Python-ASN1:
  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
  <citation>pyasn1</citation> This is another ASN1
  encoder/decoder for Python. By studying its source code I got a better
  understanding of how ASN.1 works.
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
  <citation>Samba</citation> I got the idea to use a stack based approach for
  building constructed types from libads, which is distributed as part of
  Samba.
  </listitem>

  </itemizedlist>
  </para>

  <para> References: </para>

  <bibliolist>
  <biblioentry>
  <abbrev>pyasn1</abbrev>
  <link xlink:href="http://pyasn1.sourceforge.net/">ASN.1 tools for
  Python</link>
  </biblioentry>
  <biblioentry>
  <abbrev>Samba</abbrev>
  <link xlink:href="http://www.samba.org/">The Samba project</link>
  </biblioentry>
  </bibliolist>

</appendix>

<appendix>
  <title>License</title>

  <para>
  The Python-ASN1 software is goverend by the following license (the "MIT"
  license):
  </para>

  <para>
  Copyright (c) 2007 the Python-ASN1 authors.
  </para>

  <para>
  Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a copy
  of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"), to deal
  in the Software without restriction, including without limitation the rights
  to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense, and/or sell
  copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the Software is
  furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:
  </para>

  <para>
  The above copyright notice and this permission notice shall be included in
  all copies or substantial portions of the Software.
  </para>

  <para>
  THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
  IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
  FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE
  AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
  LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
  FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER DEALINGS
  IN THE SOFTWARE.
  </para>
</appendix>

</book>
